Suchismit **Mahapatra**

LinkedIn, Sunnyvale, CA

🗆 716-435-8865 | 🔀 suchismi@buffalo.edu | # https://schrilax.github.io/ | 🛅 suchismit | 📇 schrilaxs | 🗟 suchismit

About Me _

I am a Senior AI Scientist/Engineer with LinkedIn, applying different ML/DL, GNN and NLP techniques to solve related problems. I have 10+ years of research and 5 years of developer experience during which I have worked on a variety of problems.

Research Interests

My research focuses on designing and implementing novel algorithms which enable large-scale learning and includes:

- Machine/Deep Learning (ML/DL)
- Natural Language Processing (NLP)

- Deep Graph/Geometric Learning (GNN)
- Nonlinear/Distributed Optimization

Academic Background

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Ph.D. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

April 2012 - June 2018

September 2010 - June 2012

- Topic: Scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods for streaming data.
- Advisors: Varun Chandola, Nils Napp & Jaroslaw Zola | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 (Transcript)

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

Buffalo, NY

M.S. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Topic: A Cold Start Recommendation System Using Item Correlation and User Similarity.
- Advisor: Rohini Srihari | GPA: 4.0 out of 4.0 | Department rank: 1 out of 555 (Transcript)

National Institute of Technology, Rourkela

Rourkela, India

August 2001 - May 2005

B.Tech. IN COMPUTER SCIENCE

- Specialization: Discrete Mathematics and Algorithms
- Cumulative Score: 77% (First class with Honors)(Transcript) | Joint Entrance Exam Rank 22 out of 400,000

Honors_

2022 Was invited to and attended the prestigious 2022 CIFAR DLRL School and OxML 2022. Sunnyvale,	C 1
2022 **********************************	, CA
2021 Completed NLP certification from NVIDIA DLI and Full Stack DL certification. Sunnyvale,	CA
2021 Reviewer for ICLR (2021 - present), ACL (2021 - present) and NeurIPS (2021 - present). Sunnyvale,	CA
2020 Was invited to and attended the prestigious Theory of Reinforcement Learning program. **Berkeley,**	CA
2019 Reviewer for ICML (2020 - present) and EMNLP 2021. Palo Alto,	CA
2019 Was invited to and attended the prestigious Foundations of Deep Learning program. **Berkeley,**	CA
2017 Won a NSF Junior Researcher Award to attend CBMS Conference on Sparse Recovery. Las Cruces,	NM
2016 Became a NVIDIA GPU Educator. Santa Clara,	CA

Skills & Proficiencies __

Python | PyTorch | TensorFlow | Keras | C/C++ | Apache MapReduce | Scala | CUDA | Hive

Research Experience _____

SENIOR SCIENTIST/ENGINEER

LinkedIn

Amobee

Sunnyvale, CA

• Firstline AI / Knowledge Graph (KG)

July 2021 - Present

Redwood City, CA

March 2020 - July 2021

- Tech Lead for Firstline AI/KG teams (10+ engineers), applying different ML/DL, GNN and NLP techniques to solve related problems.

SCIENTIST I • Developed a novel bidding strategy based on Win Price (WP) estimation

- Developed and productionized a novel bidding strategy using nonlinear ML based approaches for estimating WP.
- Built a Factorization Machine (FM/FFM) based ML pipeline for usage in production
 - Led efforts to build a FM/FFM based ML pipeline using a novel sparse matrix formulation that can handle high modality features.
- Incorporating user embeddings into existing ML/DL models to improve performance
 - Trained BERT/GAN based generative models to construct user embeddings for usage by our existing models.

OCTOBER 18, 2022

Criteo Al Lab Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST July 2018 - December 2019

- · Improve Click-through and Sales prediction
 - Enhanced existing production Click-through and Sales prediction pipeline using nonlinear ML techniques. Improved stability of our new models significantly from +50% to +5%. A/B test using new models resulted in +3-6% uplift in long-term RexT on all platforms.
- Theoretical aspects of Deep Learning (working with Noureddine El Karoui)
 - Working towards understanding kernel and manifold specific aspects of theoretical deep learning.
- Resolving the posterior-collapse issue in Seq2Seq learning
 - Developed a quantization based approach towards resolving the posterior-collapse issue. 🔼

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2018 - May 2018

- RESEARCH ASSISTANT • Parallelized Hierarchical Clustering (worked with Haimonti Dutta)
- Worked towards developing a novel parallel hierarchical clustering algorithm using activization strategies.
- Kernel Manifold Learning (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed novel manifold Learning techniques motivated from Gaussian Processes. 🔀

Criteo Al Lab Palo Alto R&D Center, CA

RESEARCH SCIENTIST INTERN

May 2017 - December 2017

- Cross-domain Query-Product (QP) modeling (worked with Suju Rajan)
- Developed a robust QP model across retailer domains via Domain Adaptation and Optimal Transport based approaches. 🔁

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

January 2017 - May 2017 RESEARCH ASSISTANT

- Representation learning via DL/NLSDR methods (worked with Varun Chandola / Nils Napp / Jaroslaw Zola)
 - Interpreting complex nonlinear processes using DL/NLSDR methods. 🔼 🛗 🛗
- Incorporating complex constraints for sparse Logistic Regression (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Worked towards solving the sparse Logistic Regression problem with hierarchical tree-based constraints.

BD Biosciences San Jose, CA

MACHINE LEARNING ALGORITHM DESIGN INTERN

June 2016 - August 2016

June 2013 - December 2015

- Fast Clustering of Flow Cytometry (FC) data
- Upscaled BD's clustering framework for high dimensional FC data upto ~16x. 🔼 🔼

University of Buffalo, The State University of New York

Buffalo, NY

Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction (worked with Varun Chandola / Jaroslaw Zola / Nils Napp)

- Developed scalable Nonlinear Spectral Dimensionality Reduction methods in a streaming setting. 🔼
- Social Network Modeling (worked with Varun Chandola)
 - Developed the xKPGM model for social network modeling. 🔼
- Volcanic Flow Prediction (worked with Abani Patra / Varun Chandola / Paul Bauman)
 - Developed a novel Gaussian Process based model for prediction of volcanic flow using GPUs.

The Research Foundation for SUNY

Buffalo, NY

June 2011 - August 2012

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

RESEARCH ASSISTANT

• Localization via Entropy Reduction (worked with Robert Platt)

- Developed a novel active localization technique via sequential reduction of entropy using OpenRAVE/ROS. 🔼 🛗

Publications

- 1. New Methods & Metrics for LFQA tasks. S. Mahapatra, V. Blagojevic and P. Bertorello. 2021 (Preprint available) 🔼
- 2. Interpretable Graph Similarity Computation via Differentiable Optimal Alignment of Node Embeddings. K. Doan, S. Manchanda, **S. Mahapatra** and C. Reddy. (To appear in SIGIR 2021)
- 3. Discretized Bottleneck in VAE: Posterior-Collapse-Free Sequence-to-Sequence Learning. Y. Zhao, P. Yu, S. Mahapatra, Q. Su and C. Chen. 2020 (Preprint available)
- 4. Learning Manifolds from Non-stationary Streaming Data. **S. Mahapatra** and V. Chandola. 2019 (Preprint available)
- 5. S-Isomap++: Multi Manifold Learning from Streaming Data. S. Mahapatra and V. Chandola. Proceedings of 5th IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2017 🔀
- 6. Error Metrics for Learning Reliable Manifolds from Streaming Data. S. Mahapatra, F. Schoeneman, V. Chandola, J. Zola, N. Napp. Proceedings of SIAM Data Mining Conference, 2017 🔼
- 7. Modeling Graphs Using a Mixture of Kronecker Models. S. Mahapatra and V. Chandola. Proceedings of the 3rd IEEE International Conference on Big Data, 2015. 🔼